<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2002-2004 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors,
  as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Welcome to curl-loader</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section id="overview">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The loader is a C-written open-source community tool, simulating 
             application load and application behavior of thousands and tens of 
             thousands HTTP/HTTPS and FTP/FTPS clients, each with its own 
             source IP-address. In contrast to other tools, curl-loader is using real 
             client protocol stacks, namely, HTTP 1.1 and FTP of 
             <a href="http://curl.haxx.se/libcurl/features.html">libcurl</a>,
             TLS/SSL of <a href="http://www.openssl.org/support/faq.html">openssl</a>, 
             and supports login and authentication flavors.
  </p>
      <p>The tool is useful for performance loading of various application services,
              using HTTP, HTTPS, FTP, FTPS, web-sites testing, and traffic generation.
              Activities of each virtual client are logged and statistics provided: resolving, connection
             establishment, sending of requests, receiving responses, headers and data 
             received/sent, errors from network, TLS/SSL and application (HTTP, FTP) levels.
  </p>
      <p> Virtual clients are grouped to the so-called batches of clients, performing
              the same sort of activities, like:
  </p>
       <p>     - authentication login;  </p>
       <p>     - user activity simulation (UAS) by fetching several urls and timeouts in between; </p>
       <p>     - logoff. </p>
      <p> The tool can be easily extended to generate telnet, tftp, ldap, etc other 
              application load, supported by the great libcurl library.
  </p>
    </section>

    <section id="features">
      <title>Features List</title>
      <p>
          Virtual clients -  up to 3000-6000 clients from every running curl-loader 
          process. Each client performs loading from its own IP-address;
      </p>
      <p>
          Loading modes: smooth, hyper and storming. Gradual increase of virtual clients
          number at loading start is an option for smooth and hyper modes;
      </p>
      <p>
           IPv4 and IPv6 addresses and URIs;
      </p>
      <p>
           HTTP 1.1, HTTPS, FTP, FTPS, TLS/SSL;
      </p>
      <p>
           HTTP authentication login with POST or GET+POST methods. Unique configurable 
           username and password for each virtual client as well as configurable posted 
           string (post-forms) are the options. Another option is loading of users with passwords 
          from a text file;
      </p>
      <p>
           HTTP logooff with POST, GET+POST, or GET (cookies); POST logoff with
            configurable posted string (post-forms);
      </p>
      <p>
            HTTP Web and Proxy Authentication (HTTP 401 and 407 responses) with 
            Basic, Digest (RFC2617) and NTLM supported;    
      </p>
      <p>
            HTTP 3xx redirections with unlimited number of redirections;
      </p>
      <p>
            HTTP cookies and DNS caches;
      </p>
      <p>
            Full customization of HTTP/FTP headers;
      </p>
      <p>
            TCP connections reuse or re-establishment is configurable;
      </p>
      <p>
            Unlimited configurable number of UAS URLs and inter-URL waiting time 
            for the smooth mode; 
      </p>
      <p>
            Mixing of HTTP, HTTPS, FTP and FTPS urls in a single batch of client configuration;   
      </p>
      <p>
            Logfile with configurable verbousness of tracing with output for 
            each virtual client. The logfile is atomatically rewinded, when reaching 
            configurable size to prevent disk crashes;
      </p>
      <p>
            File with status and statistics per each virtual client;
      </p>
      <p>
            Dialog GUI guided creation of configuration files and well as pre-cooked 
            configuration examples;
      </p>
      <p>
            Load Status GUI and load status output to file;
      </p>
      <p>
            Detailed loading statistics at Load Status GUI and to file;
      </p>
       <p>Here is a screenshot:</p>
      <p>
          <img src="images/black_screen.jpg" alt="curl-loader screenshot" />
       </p>
    </section>

    <section id="license">
      <title>License</title>
      <p>
             Actually it is GPL2 due to the code from 
            <a href="http://linux-net.osdl.org/index.php/Iproute2">iprouted2</a>. 
           If required, we can also consider GPL-compartible BSD-like license, and/or make it configurable.
      </p>
     </section>

    <section id="authors">
      <title>Authors</title>
      <p>
         Robert Iakobashvili (coroberti et gmail.com) and Michael Moser (moser.michael et gmail.com), both
         from Israel.
      </p>
     </section>
     <section id="success-usage">
     <title>Successfully Used</title>
       <p>
           To simulate HTTP/S load of thousands of clients against authentication 
   gateway for testing of the gateway performance in various scenarios.

    curl-loader supplied HTTP/S client load against Apache web-server with the 
    gateway in the middle, where the gateway made a browser hijacking and HTTP- 
    redirection of the curl-clients to the HTTPS url at the gateway's own 
    web-server. HTTPS page of the web-server provided a POST form to the user
    with username and password for the client/user authentication against
    an external AAA (RADIUS) server. If the authentication was OK, user (a libcurl
    virtual client object) was allowed to enter the Internet and to perform some
    sort of simulated by curl-loader network activity, namely, fetching urls and 
    sleeping in between them. After enjoying Internet, user was coming to logoff.
      </p>
       <p> 
          To test web-server pages, authenticating tens and hundred thousand of
    clients, where each client comes to a HTTPS url using GET method and is
    redirected by the web-server to another url, providing authentication POST 
    form with username and password. After successful authentication of a client
    the web-server was setting to the client server-cookies. Client activities were 
    further simulated by fetching urls and sleeping in between. Clients were 
    doing logoff using GET-method to the web-server logoff-url, where the cookies
    were used by the web-server to verify clients identity.
      </p>
       <p>
    To generate Gbps traffic from thousands of TCP/HTTP clients and to test the 
    impact of thousands of firewalling and NAT iptables/ipset rules and 
    hundreds of the rules being added/deleted each second at performance of a 
    gateway device.

    curl-loader provided client load against Apache web-server fetching a 
    url with a gigabyte file, thus, creating a permanent heavy-load 
    traffic, containing thousands of tcp-streams at the gateway in the middle.  
      </p>

<!--      <p>You can also extend the functionality of Forrest via 
      <a href="site:plugins">plugins</a>,
      these will often come with more samples for you to out.</p>
-->
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
